<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-28T21:58:18-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">TheCarbonCaudex</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Carbon Caudex</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/jekyll/update/2020/08/27/Introduction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Carbon Caudex" /><published>2020-08-27T14:07:16-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-27T14:07:16-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/jekyll/update/2020/08/27/Introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/jekyll/update/2020/08/27/Introduction.html">&lt;p&gt;We live on a carbon planet. We are carbon life. We have a carbon problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Carbon Caudex is a collection of writings by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/erikafreeman&quot;&gt;Erika C. Freeman&lt;/a&gt; and colleagues that discusses the story of Earth’s carbon. We don’t know how much carbon the Earth holds, nor do we fully comprehend its fluxes and storage. We have characterized millions of carbon compounds, yet we have only just begun to explore the richness of carbon chemistry. There are many fundamental biological and ecological mysteries that remain inextricably linked to the behaviours of carbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caudex. A stem or rootstock of a plant. Here we collate, disseminate, and share understanding of the root, or caudex, of the carbon cycle and the carbon problem on planet earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This webpage also contains several short essays and how-tos on other (mostly) related topics including: microbiology, botany, electronics, coding, remote sensing, the philosophy of science, logic and reasoning, statistics, and the occasional interlude of real-life stories, opinion and ethnobotany.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">We live on a carbon planet. We are carbon life. We have a carbon problem.</summary></entry></feed>